<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<books>
  <book ID="pkynk_cislocational" Title="{{W|The Empty Space Above}}">
    <page>
I sat about a campfire one night, the air crisp and sharp with starlight, and my traveling companion sat down with me. She had not been with me when the suns rose, and she would be elsewhere once they rose again. But in this crystallized moment, we sat across the fire from each other.

She was not of this place; I was not of hers. We were not afraid. We broke our bread together and stared into the ever-shifting flames. If I had stayed fast for a thousand thousand years, the fire would never look quite the same, and yet it would never change; it would never be aught but a fire.
    </page>
    <page>
In her hand -- many jointed, many fingered -- she held a disc of sharded glass. The firelight glinted about its countenance. It was wound about with etchings, legion and demanding, feathered through its matrix more precise than any living hand could trace.

She ran a thumb around its limned edge, and in the catch of the pad of her finger the disc shimmered with sound, resonating purer than a breath of air.

And I sat comfortably lost in the endless patterns, the whirring of the fire and the twinkle of the disk. And then, she spoke.
    </page>
    <page>
"On this world, you must walk. Twenty-nine parasangs there are between Vequina and Anterra, and so twenty-nine parasangs you must march across your land, your reeds and plains, your sanguine storms. But let's say you are of another place. A speck on the firmament where the ancients of your ancients dared to blaspheme against Distance herself.

"And so artifacts they created, summarizing engines that see and know you through and through, and decompose your thoughtstuff to be reconstituted elsewhere.

"But for all their wit and guile in their courting of Distance, a crueler master they found in Time. There are moments between the departure and arrival where you are nowhere, no one, nothing. To leap the petty span of a day's walk, it appears to your slow and gelled mind instantaneous. Now you are here; now you are there. 

"But the sliver of Time therein cannot be ignored. Across the whole of a celestial body, one geodesic to its twin, the distance forces apart the moment of here and the moment of there like an axe through saltbitten wood.
    </page>
    <page>
"Say these ancients of ancient beings consumed your world and left it like the husk of a beetle, dashed against the void of space. Say life clung to it still, stubborn, temeretic. And say you and yours unwound the secrets those Eaters tied up. Say they discovered, if not the how, the what of this perversion of space.

"Another thread. Let's say your body feels heavy on you. Let's say the beat of your heart twinges in you, and the writhing of your intestines coils around your mind, and your every step inextricably reminds you that you are solid, you are flesh, you are bound to the soil and the salt and you cannot be let go.

"And say you come of age. Say you are brought down past the salt river to the deepness of the maw of the earth, and have light and weaponry and sustenance put into your pack. You are told to simply explore, to see and experience, to return when you feel ready, when you know you must.
    </page>
    <page>
"And nothing of note happens for the first three days -- a firefight, a sip of water shared with a wise leader. Until, you happen upon a cache of those ancients of ancients. And you find inside a disc that thrums, that itches to be held.

"And you do.

"You take it out, and your fingers find a recess at its core, and press firm.

"And you are free.
    </page>
    <page>
"You are doused in the exultation of being partial, of being the barest wisp of flesh while your nerves are sprayed across the stars. The skin comes off in stripes, in winding tiles, infinitesimal seams unspooling off you into the none.

"The barest air bites the underside of the skin as the fascia revealed underneath steams into the firmament. Your organs are plucked from you one by one like grapes from the vine. You are transported, but you are not in stasis -- in the journey you writhe and burst. 

"A smear of skin Here prickles with the cold felt There, a crack of light strikes the eye There and your pupil dilates Here and the in-between shivers in its honor. Tangles of blood hang in the air in knots, lest they intersect their vessels to come. Neurons scream into the void, scream in joy and pain and worship.
    </page>
    <page>
"But it is over too soon. Hearing, first -- the red and wet slaps of flesh adhering to flesh. Your sight filters back in fits and shards. Your skin wraps around yourself and the bones fill in underneath.

"The seams rejoin.

"Your organs throb as they are returned to you, one by one, and you can feel the weight and weft of each. The plumbing is connected. Your heart beats. Your blood has touched the sky, the sun, every particle of dust in every galaxy; now it is marshalled back into its circuit, cold but warming against the endless undulation.

"And you weep, you weep at what you have lost and what you have been given. And the tears are hot on your face and you wish you could not feel them.
    </page>
    <page>
"But after a time you get up. And you feel the need to be of air and light and space again. Your body betrays you, solid as you stand, but you go. Further. Always further. Past the village, past the parasang, past Moghra'yi and the uncounted lands beyond. To lands where they have not lost the secret of leaping past the lip of the world.

"Beating Distance at her own game. Making a mockery of her parley with Time."

The fire crackled down to ash as my eyes closed on themselves. I dreamt of empty space, of knowledge I could not hold. The sunslight woke me. And she was gone.
    </page>
  </book>
</books>